1990年  第六十二届奥斯卡  最佳外语片
本片曾荣获以下电影奖项 第四十二届戛纳电影节评委会特别大奖(1989) 第二届欧洲电影奖最佳男演员(1989) 第二届欧洲电影奖评审委员特别奖(1989) 第四十七届全球奖最佳外语片(1990) 第四十四届英国电影学院奖最佳外语片(1991) 第四十四届英国电影学院奖最佳电影配乐(1991) 第四十四届英国电影学院奖最佳原着剧本(1991) 第四十四届英国电影学院奖最佳男演员(1991) 第四十四届英国电影学院奖最佳男配角(1991)
制片人: 佛朗哥·克里斯塔尔迪
编剧: 朱塞佩·多纳托雷
主演: 安东列奥·阿特利里
主演: 恩祖·卡纳瓦勒
主演: 艾萨·丹尼埃利
主演: 里奥·加洛塔
主演: 马克·莱昂纳蒂
主演: 普派拉·麦吉欧
主演: 阿奈瑟·纳努
主演: 里奥普尔多·特里斯特
主演: 萨瓦特利·卡西欧
主演: 塔努·茨马若萨 尼古拉·蒂·平托
主演: 罗伯塔·莱娜 厄尔尼诺·泰祖
主演: 雅克·贝汉
主演: 菲利浦·诺瓦雷
艺术指导: 安德烈·克利桑蒂
服装设计: 比阿特丽斯·波尔多纳
影片剪辑: 马里奥·莫瑞
制片人: 米农·巴贝拉 瑞坎杜·卡奈瓦 里罗·卡波阿诺
摄影师: 布拉斯克·朱拉多
原创音乐: 埃尼奥·莫里康内
制作: 佛朗哥·克里斯塔尔迪
导演: 朱塞佩·多纳托雷
【天 堂 电 影 院】
是的 沙瓦托 沙瓦托狄维塔
Yes, Salvatore. Salvatore De Vita.
什么意思? 你不认识他?
What do you mean? you don't know him?
对 没错 我是他母亲
Yes, that's it. I'm his mother.
我从西西里打来 找了他一整天
I'm calling from Sicily, the whole blessed day.
我知道了 不在那里
I see, not there.
那请问 你能告诉我...?
Then please, can you tell me...?
号码656-22-056
656-22-056
谢谢 再见
Thank you. Good-bye.
妈妈 打也是白打
Mama, it's useless to call.
他很忙 到处跑
He's a busy man,could be anywhere.
他一定不记得了
He won't remember anymore.
算了 他已经30年没回来了
Come on, let it go. He hasn't been here in 30 years.
你了解他的性格
You know how he is.
他会记得的
He'll remember.
我肯定他会记得 我比你更了解他
I'm sure he'll remember. I know him better than you.
如果他发现我们没告诉他
If he finds out later we didn't tell him
他一定会生气
he'll be angry.
我要找沙瓦托狄维塔先生
I'd like to talkto Mr. Salvatore De Vita.
我是他的母亲
I'm his mother.
沙瓦托 几点了?
Salvatore. what time is it?
很晚了
Very late.
抱歉 我没办法联络到你
I'm sorry. There was no way to let you know.
去睡觉吧
Go back to sleep.
你母亲来电话了
Your mother called.
她把我当成了别人
She took me for someone else.
你对她说了什么?
What'd you tell her?
我假装了很长时间 我不想让她失望
I played along. I didn't want to disappoint her.
我们聊了很久
We had a long talk.
她说你有30年没去看过她了
She said you haven't visited her in 30 years.
她想见你时 她会来罗马
When she wants to see you, she comes to Rome.
她打电话只说了这些?
She called just to say that?
不 她说有个人死了 叫艾费多
No. She said someone's died...someone named Alfredo.
明天举行葬礼
The funeral is tomorrow.
他是谁 亲戚吗?
Who is he, a relative?
不是 睡吧
No. Go to sleep.
这个小子要把我害死 我还怎么做弥撒?
The boy will be my death. How can I say Mass?
"上帝啊 我们希望你满意你的祭品"
Lord God, we ask you to be pleased with the sacrifice
"我们以卑谦和悔悟的心贡献给你"
we offer you with humble and contrite heart.
"请..."
Cleanse...
多多!
Toto!
"请赦免我们的罪"
Cleanse me from my sin.
迟点总比没有好
Better late than never.
要我说几次? 没有铃声 我会忘词
How often must I say it? Without the bell, I lose my place.
只知道睡 你晚上干什么了 吃?
Always sleeping. What do you do at night, eat?
神父 在我家我们中午都不吃东西
Father, at my house we don't even eat at noon.
是兽医这么说的 所以我很累
The veterinarian says so. That's why I'm tired.
我知道你为什么累 不要以为我不知道
I know why you're tired. Don't think I don't.
现在滚回家吧 我还要有事要忙
Now run along home. I've something to do.
我能来吗?
Can I come?
不 你不能
No, you cannot.
能 能!
Yes, yes!
多多 出去!
Toto, out!
我想去! 我想去!
I want to! I want to!
不行就是不行
Not for any reason.
艾费多
Alfredo.
艾费多!
Alfredo!
是!
Yes!
你可以开始了
You can start.
又来了
Here we go again.
银幕没对好!
The frame!
(底层社会)
(主演: 尚嘉宾)
(导演: 尚雷诺)
佩佩 有一天我们会拥有一切
Pepe, one day we'll have it all.
我们会一起远走高飞...
We'll go away together...
过着舒适的生活...
live the easy life...
在没有人认识我们的地方
where no one knows us.
忘了吧
Forget it.
你不再爱我了
You don't love me anymore.
不!
Never!
两双特价!
One pair, two pairs!
100里拉! 纯尼龙袜!
100 lire! Real nylon!
你不能来这里
You mustn't come here.
我跟你说了一次又一次 就像对着墙说的
I told you and told you...like talking to a wall.
万一胶片着火...
If the film catches fire...
像你这样的小鬼 轰!
little as you are, you'll go up... boom!
马上变成一块木炭
"And turn into a chunk of charcoal."
油腔滑调
Like to wag your tongue
我早晚剪了你的舌头
One day, I'll cut it off.
就像这样
Like that.
可以给我吗?
Can I have it?
快说啊 可以给我吗?
Come on, can I have it?
可以吗?
Well, can I?
不行!
No!
说过了! 还电影时我得把它接回去
Deaf as a post! I have to splice it back before I return the film.
你烦死了!
What a pest you are!
还电影时这些为什么不接回去?
Why didn't you splice these when you gave the films back?
有时候我找不到位置 就放这里
Sometimes I can't find the right place, so they stay here.
反正吻戏太多了
Anyway, they kiss too much.
那就给我吧
Then I can have them.
不行 过来
No. Now look, come here.
在踢你屁股前 我先跟你做个约定
Before I kick your fanny, I'll make you a deal.
那些底片都送给你
All those are yours...a present.
谢谢
Thanks.
但是第一 你不能来这里
But one, you keep out of here,
第二 它们由我保管 懂吗?
and two, they stay with me. Got it?
好
All right.
好 一言为定 现在快滚
Right. Then we agree. Now scram.
这算什么约定?
What kind of a deal is that?
我的东西为何要你保管?
If they're mine, how come you keep them?
别再回来 否则我会揍你!
Don't come back,or I'll thrash you!
先开枪 再思考
"Shoot first, think later."
懦夫才没有这种能耐
"This is no job for weaklings, traitorous dog."
你这个肮脏的猪
"Hey, you! Dirty swine,
别碰那些金子!
hands off that gold!"
黑心的猪 离我远点
"Blackhearted pig, stay away from me...
否则我就打烂你的脸
or I'll smash your face in."
妈妈
Mama
仗打完了 但是...为什么爸爸还不回来?
the war's over, but...why doesn't Papa come back?
这些天他会回来的 你会看到的
He'll come back, you'll see. One of these days.
我不记得他了
I don't remember him.
苏俄在哪里?
Where's Russia?
来回都要好几年
It takes years to get there and years to come back.
睡吧 很晚了
Go to bed. It's late.
你能骗得了你妈妈 但骗不了我!
You can hoodwink your mother, but not me!
拿到文凭然后当警察! 懒骨头!
Get your diploma and join the police! Lazybones!
什么都不会! 滚回去学习!
Good-for-nothing! Get in there and study!
五乘以五是多少?
Well? How much is 5 times 5?
三十
30.
安静!
Silence!
背九九乘法表的五 笨蛋
Table of 5's, dim wit.
一五得五 二五得十
1 times 5 is 5 2 times 5 is 10...
三五一十五 四五二十
3 times 5 is 15 4 times 5 is 20...
五乘以五呢?
5 times 5?
四十
40.
安静
Silence!
波恰
Boccia...
二十五
25.
不会乘法表 将来连工作都找不到
Learn your tables, or you'll never get a job.
最后一次 五乘以五是多少?
For the last time what is 5 times 5?
圣诞节!
Christmas!
我买票了 我来看电影
I paid to get in. I'm seeing the movie.
给我下来 小坏蛋 回你的座位去
Get down from there, you devil. Go back to your seat.
比兔子还烦 到处乱跑
Worse than rabbits. They're all over the place.
小崽子
Little monsters.
我要去俄勒岗 在我的牧场等我
I'm off to Oregon. Wait for me at my ranch.
等一个死人?
Wait for a dead man?
一部众星云集的电影...
A star-studded cast...
约翰韦恩 克莱儿崔佛
featuring John Wayne Claire Trevor
(驿马车)
大家好!
Hello, everyone!
问好都不行?
Can't I say hello?
今天连放两场
Double feature today.
那怎么了? 我是来睡觉的
So? I'm here to sleep.
你抽什么烟?
What's your smoke?
美国的
Americans.
剪掉新闻 艾费多!
Cut the news, Alfredo!
(反抗运动纪念大会)
意大利永远不会忘记
Italy never forget
勇敢的游击队员
the brave guerrillas,
从事地下活动的人
The men and women who fought in secret
他们日前重聚于罗马
reunited in Rome...
为了举行第一次反抗示威运动
for the first Resistance Rally.
(大地震动)
(主演: 西西里渔夫)
(导演: 维斯康堤)
上面写着什么?
What does it say?
我是文盲
I'm illiterate.
你也是?
You, too?
是
yes
辛苦工作12小时
Twelve hours of blood and sweat...
带回家的却勉强不至于饿死
to bring home barely enough to keep from starving.
虽然他们收网时是满的
Yet their nets when they pulled them up, were full.
一次只能赚7750里拉
each time can only earn 7750 lire.
却都被那些混蛋榨光了
but most is exploited by the wretch.
一直都是这样
always he does.
别的村子也一样
so the other villages.
我就知道!
I knew it!
20年来我看电影没有看到一次接吻
Twenty years I've gone to movies and never saw a kiss.
什么时候才有?
And when will we?
王八蛋!
Kiss my ass!
你和你 去工作
You and you, to work.
那我呢?
What about me?
去找史达林要工作吧
Go get a job from Stalin.
他的时代会来临的 就算在这儿 等着瞧吧
His day will come, even here. You watch.
老是不找我
I always get left out.
好电影 那个孩子演得真好
Good movie. The kid really acted well.
那个年轻人真倒霉
Too bad he was so unlucky.
他买那个船太傻了
What a jackass to buy that boat.
白痴 你根本就没看懂
Idiot, you didn't get it at all.
好吧 小伙子 你从早工作到晚
Right, boys, you work from dawn to dusk.
还不要求工资
And don't ask how much it pays.
妈妈
Mama.
我等了一整天 你买牛奶了?
I waited all day. You got milk?
没有
No.
钱呢?
The money?
被偷了
Stolen.
你拿去看电影了?
You spent it on movies?
是
Yes.
电影 总是看电影!
Movies, always movies!
玛丽亚太太 别打了 别生气
Signora Maria, wait. Leave him alone. Go easy.
你为什么撒谎?
And you, why do you tell lies?
你是免费进去的 快告诉妈妈
You know you got in free. Tell your mother.
可能他在里面把钱丢了
Maybe he lost the money inside.
多少?
How much?
50里拉
50 lire.
你今天捡到什么 在座位底下?
What'd you find tonight, under the seats?
一把梳子...
A comb.
两片鞋跟...
Two shoe lifts.
一罐烟草...
Can of tobacco
...还有50里拉
and 50 lire.
看到没有?
See?
谢谢你 艾费多
Thank you, Alfredo.
晚安
Good night.
再见
See you.
我们回家吧
Let's go home
我的反应很快吧
I understood right away.
广场是我的! 我的广场!
The square is mine!It's my square!
已经午夜了 午夜了!
It's midnight. Midnight!
出去! 我要关闭广场
Out! Shoo! I have to close the square.
走路很累吧 神父?
Hard on the feet, eh, Father?
去的时候是下坡 有圣人相助
Going, it's all downhill and all the saints help out.
但是回来的时候 圣人只会看着
But coming back, the saints just watch.
这也许是天意
If that's God's will.
晚上见
See you tonight.
怎么了?
What's wrong?
脚疼
my foot hurts.
脚疼?
foot hurts?
这次是你的脚 毛病还真多
Your foot this time. Always something.
我们怎么办? 怎么办?
What can we do?
艾费多 你认识我爸爸吗?
Alfredo, did you know my father?
问得好 我的确认识
What a question. And how I knew him.
他高瘦 开朗
Tall, thin, jolly,
胡子跟我一样帅
with a nice moustache like me.
总是微笑 很像克拉克盖博
Always smiling. A lot like Clark Gable.
艾费多?
Alfredo
什么事?
What?
现在我长大了要上五年级了
Now that I'm older and go to fifth grade...
就算我不能进放映室
I don't say I should come in the booth...
总能和你做朋友吧?
but can't we at least be friends?
以外表选朋友 以智慧选敌人
"I choose my friends for looks, my enemies for intelligence."
你太狡猾 不能当我的朋友
You're too foxy to be my friend.
我经常告诉我的孩子
I always tell my children...
交友要谨慎
"Be careful how you choose your friends."
你又没有小孩
You haven't got any children.
等我有了 自然会说
When I do, I'll tell them.
不哭 不哭 没事了
Don't cry, don't cry. It's all right.
火已经灭了 没事了 我在这儿呢
The fire's out. It's over. I'm here.
怎么了?
What happened?
死小孩!
Monster!
你妹妹差点被烧死
Your little sister could've burned to death.
都是你害的!
And all your fault!
我叫你别把底片放在床下靠近火盆
I told you not to keep your film under the bed by the fire pan.
照片也烧坏了!
Even the photographs burned!
差点把房子也烧了
Nearly set fire to the house.
你和你的烂电影!
You and your stupid movies!
你这把年纪了还和小孩玩不丢脸吗?
Aren't you ashamed at your age to play with a boy?
为什么看着我? 我又没做什么
Why look at me? What did I do?
谁给的他底片?
Who gave him the film?
不要再给他了 他都要疯了 疯了!
Don't do it again. He goes crazy. Crazy!
我听到的都是电影 艾费多
All I hear is movies, Alfredo.
艾费多 电影!
Alfredo, movies!
你发誓以后不让他进电影院 发誓!
Swear you won't let him in again. Swear it!
我向你保证
You have my word.
上帝答应我 会派你爸爸回来教训你
God grant me this. Send your father home to whip you!
爸爸不会回来了 我知道为什么
Papa won't come back, and I know why.
他死了
He's dead.
没这回事
That's not true.
他一定会回来的
You'll see, he'll come back.
他们抽烟抽得就像个烟囱
They smoke like chimneys.
不行 去买张票
No. Go buy a ticket.
不行!
No!
出了什么事?
What was that?
我要宰了你们! 你们给我走着瞧!
I'll make mincemeat of you! You'll reckon with me!
混蛋!
Asshole!
安娜阿姨
Signora Anna!
艾费多
Alfredo.
不要骂我 阿姨让我把午饭给你送过来
Don't blame me. Your wife told me to bring your lunch.
拿来
Give it to me.
我告诉了妈妈 底片不是你给的
I told my mother you didn't give me the film.
不是你的错
It wasn't your fault.
我以为底片会着火是个玩笑
I thought it was a joke about film catching fire.
我来就是想告诉你这些 那我走了
I just wanted to tell you. Now I'll go.
多多 过来
Toto, come here.
来 坐下
Come on, come sit down.
听着 我10岁就干起了这行
Now listen. I got into this business at age ten.
以前 我们没有先进的机器
Back then, we didn't have fancy machines.
电影没有声音
Movies were silent.
放映机得用手去转把手
You turned the projector by hand with a crank.
整整的一大天! 它又很重 那个该死的把手
The whole live long day! And it was hard, that damn crank.
要是你累了 动作慢了一点
If you got tired and slowed down a bit...
就像一个炮弹 呼! 东西都着了
like a shot, whoom! everything burned.
那为什么不教我?
So why not teach me?
现在已经没有把手 而且又是那么容易
Now that there's no crank and it's dead easy.
因为我不想教
Because I don't want to.
这份工作不适合你
It's no kind of job for you.
你就像一个奴隶 总是很孤单
You're like a slave and always alone.
一部电影你要看一百遍 你没有别的事可做
You see a film 100 times. You've nothing else to do.
只能对着葛丽泰嘉宝和泰隆鲍华说话 像个疯子
You talk to Garbo and Tyrone Power like a loony bird.
你像个驴一样工作
You work like a burro.
就连复活节 圣诞节也不例外
Even holidays Easter, Christmas.
你只有在星期五才能休息
You only get Good Friday off.
这还是托耶稣受难的福
And if they hadn't stuck Christ on a cross we'd even work then.
那你为什么不换工作呢?
So why don't you change jobs?
因为我是个笨蛋
Because I'm a nitwit.
周围还有谁会用放映机?
Who else around here could run a projector?
没人会 只有我这样的傻瓜会用
Nobody. It takes an imbecile like me.
我的运气一向不好
And I never had any luck.
你还想干我这没出息的行业?
So! Want to be a stick-in-the-mud like me? How about it?
不想
No.
这就对了 多多
Attaboy, Toto.
我告诉你是为你好
I only tell you for your own good.
窝在这里 夏天闷死人
Cooped up here. Suffocate in summer,
冬天冷死人 空气又不好
freeze to death in winter. Breathing fumes.
挣的钱只够养个小鸡
And you earn chicken feed.
你一点都不喜欢这个工作吗?
Don't you like anything about it?
日久生情 有时候你听到...
Oh, it grows on you. Sometimes you listen...
满屋子人哈哈大笑
and the house is full of people giggling and laughing.
你也会很开心
Then you're happy too.
那种感觉很好
It makes you feel good to hear them.
好像是你在逗他们笑
Like you're the one who made them laugh
你让他们忘记烦恼
who made them forget their troubles.
我喜欢这样
That part I like.
你不会懂的 你在干嘛?
I might as well speak Greek! What're you up to?
假装在听 趁机乱动
Pretend to listen, then play the clown!
你母亲说得对! 你这个糊涂蛋!
Your mother's right! You're a scatterbrain!
这个淘气蛋怎么做的? 他看看就会了
How'd the rascal do it? He learned by watching.
多多 听着
Toto listen.
我要叫经理禁止你入场
I'm telling the manager not to let you in!
我还要叫神父不要让你当助祭!
And I'll see Father Adelfio! No more altar boy!
你完了
Finished!
艾费多! 我听不到!
Alfredo! Up yours!
进球了!
goal!
我的足球彩票中奖了!
I got it! I won! I won the football lottery!
拿坡里人中奖了!
The Neapolitan won the lottery!
拿坡里的奇奇欧中奖了!
Hey, Ciccio from Naples won the lottery!
北方人就是走运
Always the northerners who hit it lucky.
广场是我的! 全是我的!
The square is mine! All mine!
别动! 你还会怕马蝇?
Hold still! Horseflies bothering you?
你的头上有一窝虱子
You got a lice factory up here.
去吧
Beat it.
你们这帮捣蛋鬼在后面干什么? 滚开!
What're you after? A smack? Get out of here.
一个商人有两家店
A merchant owns two stores.
一家卖水果...
In one, he sells fruit.
坐下
Be seated.
教授 参加年级文凭资格考试的人来了
Professor, the auditors taking the exam for the grade school diploma.
进来
Come in.
安静
Silence!
多多 多多
Toto, Toto.
忘恩负义...
Rotten little stinker.
多多 帮帮我
Toto, help me.
安静!
Silence!
我不会做这个该死的题
I can't do this damn thing.
安静!
Silence!
多多
Toto!
好吧
OK.
(逃犯的手铐)
法兰契斯柯马赛纳
Francesco Messana...
你被捕了
you're under arrest.
漂亮!
Good riddance!
谢天谢地!
Thank goodness!
王八蛋! 去死吧!
Kiss my ass! Pencil pusher!
这里容易起火
Right here is where it can catch fire.
一起火就切断这里和这里
If it does, cut here and here,
否则整卷都会烧起来 懂了吗?
or the whole reel will burn. Got it?
懂了 艾费多
Yes. Alfredo.
从来没有 我们从来没有放过那种镜头
Never. We'll never have that here.
哪一面是正面?
Which side is the gelatin on?
挺好吃的
It tastes good.
艾费多 没对好
Alfredo, the frame!
影片备忘录一定要留好
Shipping invoice for the film. Always keep them.
我会的 艾费多
I will, Alfredo.
千万别忘了
Don't ever forget.
(化身博士)
这个给你 今天你自己放电影
This is for you. Today you load the reels yourself.
好高啊!
It's so high!
现在你可以独自操作了
Now you can run it alone.
站好 不要动!
Hold it. Don't move!
真火辣!
What a build!
该我了! 该我了!
My turn! My turn!
跟贝比诺说再见吧 他要去德国了
Say good-bye to Peppino. He's leaving for Germany.
再见
Good-bye
你为什么不跟他说再见?
Why don't you say good-bye?
我爸爸说他是共产党
My father says he's a communist.
上帝保佑你 妈妈
God keep you, Mama.
他真的要在德国找工作吗?
Will he really find work in Germany?
谁知道 就像买彩票...
You never know. Like playing the lottery...
你靠希望活着
you live on hope.
去你的烂国家!
Screw this country!
到德国工作吧 史达林的走狗
Go work in Germany, you and your Stalin.
再见 妈妈
Good-bye, Mama.
再见 贝比诺! 快回来啊!
Good-bye, Peppino! Come back soon!
我们会再见的
We'll see you.
再见了!
Good-bye!
真好 德国比苏俄近
Lucky thing Germany is closer than Russia.
六年之后
After six years,
春季时装重新登场
the return of spring fashion.
清新自然 有别于战时的浮夸
Fresh and breezy, unlike the pompous styles of wartime.
我要宰了你们!
I'll make mincemeat of you!
你们给我走着瞧!
"You'll reckon with me!"
没错!
Right!
驻俄国军弟兄再传噩耗
Another sad page, in the tragedy of our men in Russia.
国防部已公布死者名单
The Defense Ministry has released a new list of ltalian dead...
又一批失踪官兵证实死亡
until now considered missing.
各地军方单位将通报姓名
The names will be posted by local military authorities.
家属亦将接获通知
Families concerned will be notified.
然而 我们不知道他埋在哪里
However, we don't know where he's buried.
这是抚恤金表格 请签名
Here's the pension form. Sign it, please.
(乱世佳人)
出去! 回家吧! 不能再加演了!
Out! Go home! We can't have another show!
很晚了 讲点道理 不能再演了
It's late. Be reasonable. We can't show it again!
有些人连看两场!
Some people sat through it twice!
我们已经等了1个小时!
We've been waiting for an hour!
明天我们有另一场电影
Tomorrow we'll have another movie.
是西部片 我保证! 回家睡觉吧
A western. Word of Honor! Go home to bed.
他们会拆了天堂(电影院)! 地狱的所有东西都会解放!
They'll wreck the Paradiso! All hell will break loose!
神父 开门
Father, open the door.
艾费多 让我们进去!
Alfredo, let us in!
我能做什么?
What can I do?
我们已经等了三个小时!
I've been waiting for 3 hours!
"暴民没有头脑 不事思考"
"A mob doesn't think. lt has a mind of its own."
史宾塞屈赛在"愤怒"里说的
Spencer Tracy said that in "Fury."
那么 你说怎么办?
Well, what do you say?
我们该让这些可怜的魔鬼看到他们的电影吗?
Shall we let the poor devils see their film?
太好了 怎么做?
Fantastic. But how?
"就算你不相信我"
"If you have no faith in me,
"也要相信你的眼睛"
have faith in what you see."
站起来过来看吧
Now get your fanny off that stool.
预备...
Get ready.
天灵灵 地灵灵
Abracadabra...
我们将它穿过墙...
and we pass through walls.
到窗外看看
Go look out the window.
艾费多 好美啊
Alfredo, it's beautiful.
看! 电影在那边!
Over there! It's the movie!
你好厉害 艾费多
Bravo, Alfredo.
谢谢 艾费多!
Thank you, Alfredo!
怎么了?
What's going on?
是个电影!
It's a movie!
你们下地狱吧
To hell with you.
艾费多 没声音!
Alfredo there's no sound!
我们要让他们如愿吗?
Shall we make them happy?
要!
Yes!
想下去吗?
Want to go down?
去吧
Go on.
老天啊
Good Lord.
去收半价
And Nunzio, half price.
知道了
I see.
麻烦买票 各位
Have to buy tickets, folks.
半价就好
Reduced rates.
少来了 广场是大家的!
Up yours! The square belongs to everyone!
不!
no!
广场是我的! 别拿那个开玩笑! 我会生气的!
The square is mine! Don't joke about that! lt makes me mad!
艾费多!
Alfredo!
救命啊!
Help!
艾费多! 不! 艾费多!
Alfredo! No! Alfredo!
艾费多 艾费多 救命啊! 救命啊!
Alfredo, Alfredo. Help! Help!
艾费多 Alfredo!
Alfredo, Alfredo!
救命啊!
Help!
可怜的艾费多 真可惜啊
Poor Alfredo. What a shame.
全烧了!
All burned!
全都烧光了!
It all burned down!
我们现在怎么办?
What do we do now?
我们再也没有娱乐了
We have no more entertainment. Nothing.
哪来的钱重建?
Where'll we get the money to rebuild?
你看奇奇欧 好时髦 你都认不出他了
Take a look at Ciccio. So spiffy, you'd hardly know him.
谁有钱重新整修?
Who has that kind of money?
(新天堂电影院)
新天堂电影院开张!
The new Cinema Paradiso!
请进 请进
Come in, come in.
欢迎!
Welcome!
电影院为你而开!
This theater is for you!
他只是个小孩
He's just a boy.
违反劳动法怎么办?
What about labor laws?
我靠关系拿到执照了
I got the license through connections.
别问我他们怎么想的
Don't ask me how their minds work.
对外 我是放映师
Officially, I'm the projectionist,
但是薪水给多多
but the money goes to Toto.
保持警觉 多多 别打瞌睡
Stay on your toes, Toto. No sleeping.
我们的灾难够多了
We've had enough disasters.
照可怜的艾费多教的去做
Do what poor Alfredo taught you.
上帝保佑你
And God bless you.
谢谢你 神父
Thank you, Father.
这是怎么了 葬礼啊?
What is this, a funeral?
日子总要过! 开心点!
Life goes on! Gaiety!
放音乐!
Music!
你喜欢那个农夫?
Do you love that farmer?
对
Yes.
那个就是他?
Is that one him?
对
Yes.
你不爱我了吗?
Don't you love me anymore?
真美啊!
Get a load of that!
我们的父啊...
Our Father
老天啊 他们在接吻!
My God, they're kissing!
我绝不看色情片
I won't watch pornography.
为奇奇欧干杯!
Three cheers for Ciccio!
新天堂有我的地方吗?
Any room for me in this new paradise?
艾费多!
Alfredo!
艾费多
Alfredo
多多 散场后送他回家
Toto. Bring him home after you close.
我走了 艾费多
I'm going, Alfredo.
我好高兴你能来
It's great you came.
在学校过得怎么样?
How're things at school?
很好
Fine,
但我现在有了工作 可能不上学了
but now that I'm working, maybe I won't go anymore.
不 不 多多 不可以休学
No. No, Toto. Don't do that.
否则你最后会很丢脸
You'll end up with egg on your face.
为什么? 那是什么意思?
Why? What does that mean?
意思是这不是你的终身事业
It means that this isn't your real work.
现在电影院需要你 而你也需要电影院
Right now the Paradiso needs you and you need the Paradiso
但这是暂时的
but it's a stopgap.
总有一天你还会做别的事
One day you'll go on to other things.
比现在重要得多的事 肯定重要得多
Things that are more important. Definitely more important.
我知道的 虽然我瞎了 但我看得更透彻
I know. Now that I've lost my sight I see better.
看到更多我以前没看到的
Things I never saw before.
这全都要感谢你的救命之恩
All thanks to you, who saved my life.
我永远不会忘记
I won't forget it.
不要那种表情
And don't look like that.
我还没有老糊涂 要证明吗?
I'm not senile yet. Want proof?
要
Yes.
那好 让我看看
Well, let's see.
例如...
For example...
现在 画面失焦了
right now, the film's out of focus.
去检查
Go check.
你说对了 艾费多 真的失焦了!
You're right, Alfredo, it's out of focus.
你怎么知道的?
How'd you know?
很难解释
Too hard to explain.
干什么? 专心看电影
What's the idea? Watch the screen.
畜牲 强奸犯!
Animals, rapists!
看 别乱摸
Look, don't touch.
我说过的它不容易着火
I told you lt doesn't catch fire.
进步总是来得太迟
Progress always comes too late.
(七对佳偶)
全世界的工人们
Workers of the world
(车站)
她是新来的
She's new.
还不错 很随和
Not bad. Approachable.
爸爸是银行经理
Father's the bank manager.
自傲 爱炫耀还很圆滑
Pride, pomp and circumstance.
那种人都表里不一 从不弄脏他的手
Jerks off with his shirt, not to get his hand dirty.
加油 哥们 加油!
Go, man, go!
抱歉
Excuse me.
什么事?
Yes?
你的丢了这个
You dropped this.
谢谢 我都没发现
Oh, thanks. I didn't even notice.
我叫沙瓦托 你呢?
My name's Salvatore. What's yours?
艾莲娜 我叫艾莲娜
Elena. My name's Elena.
我想告诉你 其实 前几天在车站...
I wanted to tell you, well, the other day at the station
小放映机? 你自己拍的?
The small projector? Your footage?
对
Yes.
你看到什么?
What do you see?
屠宰场工人在宰杀小母牛
Slaughterhouse workers killing a heifer.
地上血流成河
Blood all over the floor, like a lake.
血泊旁边还有一头母牛 也要死了
Over the lake comes another heifer about to die.
怎么停住了? 我们看到什么?
Why'd you stop? What do we see?
没什么 我们什么都看不到 画面很模糊
Nothing. We don't see anything. It's all fuzzy.
一个女人
A woman.
是个女人
It's a woman.
对 我在车站看到的一个女孩
Yes, a girl I saw at the station.
她长什么样子?
What's she like?
她很美
She's very nice.
跟我同岁 苗条 棕色长发
My age, slim, long hair, brown.
大眼睛 非常蓝 纯洁而且坦白
Big eyes, very blue, honest and direct.
嘴唇上有个小美人痣
A little beauty markon her lip.
非常小 近看才看得到
Very small.You only see it up close.
她微笑时 你感觉像...我不知道
When she smiles, you feel like...l don't know.
爱
Love.
这就是爱
我知道的是...蓝眼睛的女人最难追
I know how it is...The blue-eyed ones are the worst.
不管你怎么做 她们都不会成为你的朋友
No matter what you do, they'll never be your friends.
什么都没用
Nothing for it.
越是煎熬 越刻骨铭心
The bigger the man, the deeper his imprint.
如果他爱上了 他只能忍受
And if he loves, he suffers,
明知道那是个死胡同
knowing it's a dead-end street.
你刚才说的这些话很美 也很伤感
That's nice, what you just said. But sad.
不是我说的
I didn't say it.
是约翰韦恩在"山上的牧羊者"中说的
It was John Waynein "The Shepherd of the Hills."
你这个老贼 艾费多!
You old pirate, Alfredo!
你好 艾莲娜
Hello, Elena.
你好 你为什么要跑?
Hello. Why're you running?
因为...
Because...
我想告诉你...
I wanted to tell you...
你记得我们什么时候...
you remember when we...
天气真好 不是吗?
Nice day, isn't it?
是啊 真的很好
Yes, really nice.
抱歉 我要走了 再见
Excuse me, I have to go. Bye.
再见
Bye
我真笨 我真笨!
What a jerk. What a jerk!
"天气真好? 不是吗? " 太傻了!
"Nice day, isn't it?" Of all the assholes!
我告诉过你 你以为我在开玩笑
I told you so. You thought I was joking.
相信我的话 蓝眼睛女孩最难追
But take it from me, the blue-eyed ones are the worst.
为什么? 一定会有办法让她明白的
But why? There must be a way to make her understand.
最好别试 对于情感 任何事都难明白...
Don't even try. With feelings, there's nothing to understand...
而且没有办法解释
and no way to explain.
好像是你创造了这个世界!
Oh, you made the world!
我无意冒犯上帝...
With due respect to the Lord...
他两三天就创造了世界
who made the world in 2, 3 days...
我会比他慢一点...
I'd have taken a bit longer...
但说得谦虚点 我会造得更好些
but in all modesty, I would've done it better.
我说过...你总是知道答案
Like I said...you always have an answer.
就为你 多多 我给你讲个故事
Just for you, Toto, I'll tell you a story.
让我们坐一会儿
Let's sit down a minute.
无尽的烦恼
Misery of miseries.
从前 一个国王...
Once a king...
为他最可爱的公主举办了一场宴会
gave a feast for the loveliest princesses in the realm.
有个卫兵看到国王的女儿从他身边走过
A soldier who was standing guard saw the king's daughter go by.
她实在太美了...
She was the most beautiful of all...
他立刻坠入情网
and he instantly fell in love.
但是一个卑微的士兵...
But what is a simple soldier...
怎么能配得上国王的女儿?
next to the daughter of a king?
后来 他终于有机会见到她...
Well, at last he succeeded in meeting her...
他告诉她 他不能没有她
and he told her he could no longer live without her.
公主被他深深的感情所打动...
The princess was so taken by the depth of his feeling...
她就告诉那个士兵...
that she said to the soldier...
"你如果连续一百个昼夜
"If you can wait...
日日夜夜守在我的阳台下...
for 100 days and 100 nights under my balcony...
最后 我就以心相许"
at the end of it, I shall be yours."
于是 士兵去等了一天...
With that, the soldier went and waited one day...
两天 然后十天 二十天
two days, then ten, then twenty.
每个晚上公主向外看...
Each evening the princess looked out...
他从来都不动!
and he never moved!
下雨 刮风 下雪 他一直在那里
In rain, in wind, in snow, he was always there.
小鸟在他头上拉屎 蜜蜂蛰他...
Birds shat on his head, bees stung him...
他还是一动不动
but he didn't budge.
到了最后 第90天...
At the end of 90 days...
他已经变得...
he had become...
苍白虚弱
all dry, all white.
眼泪从他的双眼流下来
Tears streamed from his eyes.
他控制不住
He couldn't hold them back.
他甚至连睡觉的力气都没了
He didn't even have the strength to sleep.
公主把一切都看在眼里
And all that time, the princess watched him.
终于到了最后 那是第九十九个夜晚...
At long last, it was the 99th night...
士兵站起来 搬起椅子 走了
and the soldier stood up, took his chair and left.
什么? 这就是结局?
What? At the end?
这就是那个结局
At the very end.
别问那是什么意思 我也不知道
And don't ask what it means. I don't know.
要是你明白了 你要告诉我
If you understand it, you tell me.
只有一个拷贝?
Only one print?
你知道我需要两个
You know I need two.
一个给新天堂 一个给邻镇
One for the Paradiso, one for the next town.
你答应过的
You promised.
海报都贴了 你要兑现承诺!
I put up posters, made commitments!
如果你对不起我 小心点!
lf you screw me, watch out!
一份拷贝给两个电影院! 你会为此付出代价的!
One print for two theaters! You'll pay for this!
我是拿坡里人
I'm from Naples
我会让你死得很难看!
and you will see it and die!
我们看了婴儿床 孩子已经睡了
We see the crib. The child's asleep.
萝莎!
Rosa!
"她的药呢? 快想办法! "
"Where is her medicine? Do something!"
律师曾告诉我
The lawyer told me.
现在我知道了
Now I know.
"律师曾告诉我"
"The lawyer told me.
"现在我知道了"
Now I know."
每个人都知道 对 每个人都应该知道
And everyone must know. Yes, everyone must know.
"每个人都知道"
"Everyone must know."
你相信我吗?
You believe me?
"你相信我吗? "
"You believe me?"
是的 我相信你
Yes, I believe you.
"是的 我相信你"
"Yes, I beIieve you."
我们的家! 梦想许久的家!
Our own home. How I've dreamed of it.
"- 我们的家! - 梦想许久的家! "
"- Our own home. - How I've dreamed of it."
托尼诺!
Tonino!
"托尼诺! "
"Tonino!"
"妈妈! "
"Mama!"
妈妈!
Mama!
"妈妈! "
"Mama!"
妈妈!
Mama!
剧终
The End.
我不喜欢它 我不喜欢它
I don't like it.I don't like it.
我为了快点剪掉了演职员名单
I cut the end credits to go faster.
快把上集拿回来 我来播新闻片
Hurry back with part one. I'll show a newsreel.
我报的警 把他带走
I'll call the police. Take him.
他看了十次了
He saw it ten times.
等一下 等一下!
Just a minute. Just a minute!
给我下集 这是上集
Give me part two. Here's part one.
快点 屋子都快挤爆了
Hurry, the house is packed.
快点 慢虫 快点摇啊!
Come on, slowpoke. Get her rolling!
快点 今天大爆满
Hurry, today is capacity crowd
快点
Come on.
畜生们 安静!
Bunch of animals. Quiet!
快点 多多 他们要暴乱了
Come on, Toto, they'll explode!
已经半小时了!
It's been a half hour!
我也没办法
What can I do?
那个混蛋呢? 我会死得很惨
Where is that son of a jackass? I'll be ruined.
安静 安静
Calm down, calm down.
我要让你知道 为了看这部电影...
I'll have you know, just to see this movie...
我丢下卧病在床的老婆...
I left my wife home sick in bed...
结果我什么都没看到
and I haven't seen a thing.
如果再过十分钟还不开始 把钱退给我们
If it's not here in ten minutes, give us back our money.
我和所有人的钱! 否则拆了你的电影院
Me and everyone here! Or with this,I'll wreck the place!
安静! 安静
Calm down! Calm down
听我说
and let me talk.
改天再放上集好了
Tell you what. I'll show part one another time.
不能再拖了
Mustn't delay any longer.
安静 安静!
Quiet, quiet!
我看过整部电影
I've seen the whole movie.
我可以说给你们听
I'll tell you the plot.
艾费多 帮个忙
Alfredo, do me a favour.
帮我缠住神父
Help me to tied the father up.
艾费多 什么事?
Alfredo, what is it?
神父
Father.
我不能...有人要告解
I can't...The Host is on the altar.
神父 我急切地需要你...
Father, I need you urgently...
因为我心存疑惑 灵魂饱受折磨
because I have doubts terrible doubts tormenting my soul.
你的灵魂
Your soul.
对
Yes
神父 我有罪
Father, I've sinned.
待会再说
Do that after.
但是你是...
But who...
待在那里 别动 假装没事
Stay there. Don't move. Just act normal.
我是沙瓦托
It's Salvatore.
你怎么在这里?
How'd you get here?
艾费多 太可怕了
Alfredo, that's a terrible thing to say.
我知道
I know.
但是现世利益上的奇迹
But take the miracle of the loaves and fishes.
怎样?
What about it?
我常在想...有可能吗?
I always wonder...how is it possible?
我要告诉你
I had to talk to you.
你好美 艾莲娜 那就是我想告诉你的
You're beautiful, Elena. That's what I wanted to tell you.
我们见面时 我老是说错话...
When we meet, I can't say anything right...
因为你令我颤抖
because you give me the shivers.
我不知道别人会怎么做
I don't know what others do in these cases.
这是我的第一次
It's my first time.
我爱上你了
But I'm in love with you.
神父 我有罪
Father, I have sinned.
我以圣父圣子圣灵之名赦免你 安心地去吧
I absolve you,in the name of the Father,Son and Holy Ghost.Go in peace.
你笑起来更美
When you laugh, you're even prettier.
沙瓦托 你很可爱 我也很喜欢你...
Salvatore, you're very sweet, and I like you very much...
但是我不爱你
but I don't love you.
没不管 我会等
I don't care. I'll wait.
等什么?
What?
等你爱上我 听我说
For you to fall in love with me. Now listen.
每晚下了班
Every night after work,
我会在站你家门外 我每天晚上都会等的
I'll come stand outside your house. And I'll wait. Every night.
你要是改变心意 请打开你的窗户
When you change your mind, open your window.
这样我就懂了
That's all. I'll understand.
你懂了吗?
You understand now?
懂了 我终于重见光明
Yes, finally, I see the light.
下次别再提异端邪说
Next time, don't talk heresy.
你在电影院大火中生还 但是一旦碰上地狱之火...
You survived the theater fire, but from the Eternal Fire...
谁也救不了你
no one can save you.
注意! 距离新年还有十五秒!
Attention! Fifteen seconds to the new year!
十四 十三 十二
14, 13, 12
十一 十 九 八...
11, 10, 9, 8...
五 四 三 二 一
5 4 3 2 1
沙瓦托
Salvatore.
电影完了 打开灯
The film is over. Turn on the light.
太棒了 我从没开过车
Oh, great. Never been driven, he said.
我们要怎么回家?
How'll we get home?
停车!
Stop!
天啊 是我父亲
Oh, God, it's my father.
你好 曼多拉先生
Hello, Mr. Mendola.
- 你好! - 你好!
- Hello. - Hello.
露天电影院 即将开始
Play at an open-air theater.
只剩下站的地方!
Standing room only!
请进 电影刚开始
Come on in. The show just started.
请把票准备好
Have your tickets ready.
心爱的沙瓦托
Salvatore, my love.
整个夏天跟我的家人在一起 没有你 日子特别漫长
A whole summer with my family, far from you, my days here go on forever.
我的眼前不断浮现你的名字 在一本书里...
I see your name everywhere in a book...
一个字谜里 一张报纸里
a crossword puzzle, a newspaper.
你总是出现在我的眼前
You're always before my eyes.
今天有一个坏消息
Today, alas, I have bad news.
十月我们要搬到巴勒摩 我会在那里上大学
In October we move to Palermo, where I'll go to university.
所以我们无法天天见面了
So we won't see each other every day.
不过别担心 不管什么时候我能离开...
But don't worry, whenever I can get away...
我会去天堂电影院找你
I'll come to you at the Paradiso.
我失明了!
I'm blind!
凭借上帝的力量 凭借人类的运行! 升起来!
By God's might, by man's running! Rise up!
为什么这个腐烂的夏天还不结束?
When will this rotten summer end?
在电影里 它早该结束了
In a film, it'd already be over.
淡出 切到暴风雨 那样不是很棒吗?
Fade-out: cut to storm. Wouldn't that be great?
告诉他们我是奥德赛!
Tell them I am Odyssey!
艾莲娜...你什么时候?
Elena...But when?
今天
Today.
你想象不到我为了来这里找的借口
You can't imagine the excuses I made up to come here.
我要去罗马服兵役 周五走
I'm doing my military service in Rome. I leave Friday.
我会到天堂电影院送你
I'll come to say good-bye at the Paradiso.
周四坐下午五点的班车到
I'll arrive Thursday, by 5 p.m. bus.
多多 或许军队弄错了 不管怎样 罗马很漂亮
Toto, Maybe the army made a mistake. Anyway, Rome is beautiful.
把明天的拷贝装好
Load the reels for tomorrow
为新手准备好
ready for the new man.
好
Yes
开心一点 我会等着你 别担心
Hey, cheer up. I'll wait for you. Don't worry.
这份工作跑不掉 我会等着 你听到了吗?
The job'll still be here. I'll wait, you hear?
别那么沮丧 来吧! 走!
Don't look so gloomy. Come on! Hup!
第三营第九连 通讯兵狄维塔 长官!
Radioman Di Vita, 3rd Battalion, 9th Company, sir!
她爸让她转学? 不可能!
Transferred her father? No way!
没有人知道她在哪儿?
And no one knows where?
你再不讲就死定了 混蛋王八蛋!
Screw you if you won't tell me! Asshole son of a bitch!
(查无此人)
乖...
Good...
过来
Come here.
你瘦了 终于回来了
You're thinner. Put you through it, eh?
他们说你从不出门 也不跟比人说话
They tell me you never go out and you never talk to anybody.
为什么?
Why?
你知道原因
You know how it is.
这是迟早要来的事
Sooner or later the time comes...
讲不讲都没有差别
whether you talk or don't talk, it's the same thing.
还不如闭嘴
So you might as well shut up.
这里好热
It's hot here.
带我去海边
Take me to the sea.
一次聚会 有个中尉偷捏女孩的屁股
At a party, a lieutenant pinches this girI's ass.
她转过身 竟然是上校的女儿
She turns around. It's the coloneI's daughter.
中尉吓得急忙说
Terrified, the lieutenant says...
"如果你的心也像我刚才摸到的那么硬"
"If your heart is as hard as what I just felt, "
"我就死定了"
"I'm a dead man."
你没见过她吗?
You haven't seen her?
没有
No.
也没有人知道她在哪
And no one knows where she is.
大概这就是天意
Probably that's how it was meant to be.
我们 我们每一个人 人人都有所追寻
We, each of us, have a star to follow.
离开这里
Get out of here.
这里被诅咒了
This land is cursed.
每天待在这里
Living here day by day...
你会把这里当成世界的中心
you think it's the center of the world.
你会相信什么都不会改变
You believe nothing will ever change.
然后你离开了...一年 两年
Then you leave...a year, two years.
等你回来时 一切都变了 牵挂也断了
When you come back, everything's changed. The thread's broken.
你来寻找的已经不在 曾经是你的也已经消失
What you came to find isn't there. What was yours is gone.
你不得不离开很长一段时间...
You have to go away for a long time...
很多年后 你回来找到你的亲友
many years before you can come back and find your people.
回到你的故乡
The land where you were born.
但是现在不可能 你比我还盲目
But now, no. It's not possible. Right now you're blinder than I am.
是谁讲的? 贾利古柏?
Who said that? Gary Cooper?
詹姆斯史都华? 亨利方达?
James Stewart? Henry Fonda?
不 多多
No, Toto.
没人说过这些
Nobody said it.
这次全是我说的
This time it's all me.
人生和电影不一样
Life isn't like in the movies.
人生辛苦多了
Life is much harder.
离开这里
Get out of here.
回到罗马去
Go back to Rome.
你还年轻 世界是你的
You're young, the world is yours.
我已经老了
And I'm old.
我不想再听你说了
I don't want to hear you talk anymore.
我想听关于你的事
I want to hear talk about you.
不要回来
Don't come back.
不要想到我们
Don't think about us.
不要回头 不要写信
Don't look back. Don't write.
不要因为思乡而放弃 忘了我们
Don't give in to nostalgia. Forget us all.
要是你放弃回来了 就别来见我
If you do and you come back, don't come see me.
我不会让你进我家 懂吗?
I won't let you in my house. Understand?
谢谢你为我做的一切
Thank you. For everything you've done for me.
不管你最后要干什么 热爱它
Whatever you end up doing, love it.
就像小时候你热爱放映机那样
The way you loved the projection booth when you were a little squirt.
他走了 多多! 再见!
He's left.Toto! Good-bye!
多多!
Toto!
来晚了点 真可惜
Got here too late, what a shame.
是多多 我知道是他
It's Toto. I knew it.
多多
Toto.
你好吗?
How are you?
看看这房子多漂亮
See how nice the house is?
我们把它全部翻新了 全都要感谢你
We had it all redone, all thanks to you.
我有个惊喜要给你 来
I have a surprise for you. Come.
累吗?
Are you tired?
葬礼前你还有时间休息
You have time to rest before the funeral.
不累 妈妈 飞回来才一个小时
No, Mama, it's only an hour by plane.
都这么多年了还告诉我这个
Don't tell me that after all these years.
来 你的东西全都在这里
Come. I put everything in here. All your things.
你来他一定很开心 多多
He must be glad you came, Toto.
他老是提到你
He always talked about you. Always.
临死前也是
Right up to the end.
他真的...他真的很爱你
He really...He really loved you.
他有东西要给你
He left something for you.
离开之前 记得来找我
Before you leave, come see me.
你过得怎么样
How have you been?
什么时候关门的?
When did you close it down?
六年前的五月 没人来了
Six years ago in May. Nobody came anymore.
您比我清楚 狄维塔先生...
You know better than l, Mr. Di Vita...
经济问题 电视 录影带
the economy, TV, videos.
老电影业已经成了回忆
The old movie business is just a memory.
政府买去盖停车场
The city bought the site for a parking lot.
周六就要拆了 真叫人难过
They're demolishing it Saturday. It's too bad.
为何叫"狄维塔先生"? 我以前是你的雇工
What's this "Mr. Di Vita"? You used to order me around.
现在你是个大人物了 这就不同了
Now that you're a big shot, it's a little different.
如果你不介意我可以叫你...多多
But, if you insist, Toto.
失陪
Excuse me.
谁会相信 小多多!
Who would've believed it...little Toto.
这是他留给你的
This is...what he left for you.
他从没有说过要见我?
He never asked to see me?
没有 从来没有
No, never.
有一次 你母亲跟他说...
Once your mother said to him...
如果他愿意 你肯定会来
that if he wanted it, you'd surely come.
他很生气 他说
He was furious. He said,
不行 多多绝对不能回来!
"No. Toto must never come back to Giancaldo!"
他没有说什么意思 他是个好人
He didn't say it to be mean. He was a good man.
谁知道他在想什么
Who knows what was going through his head.
临终前 他说了一些怪事
Towards the end, he said strange things.
就连要闭眼前的那一刻...
A moment before he closed his eyes...
他还告诉你母亲不要让你知道
he told your mother she mustn't let you know.
多多 你在想什么?
Toto, What're you thinking?
我一直害怕回来
Just that I've always been afraid to come back.
如今 过去这么多年了
And now, after all these years,
我以为我更坚强了 我已经忘掉了很多事情
I thought I was stronger that I'd forgotten a lot of things.
结果我发现我只是回到原点...
But in fact, I find I'm right back where I was...
仿佛从没有离开过
as if I'd never been away.
但我看看四周 却什么都认不出来
Yet when I look around, I don't recognize anyone.
而你 妈妈...我离弃了你
And you, Mama...I deserted you.
我像强盗一样什么都没说就跑开了
Ran out on you like a bandit without any explanation.
我从不要求什么 你也不需要向我解释
I never asked for any. You don't have to explain to me.
我一直相信你做的都是对的
I always thought it was good what you did.
你何必耿耿于怀
Why harp on it?
你离开是对的 你做了你想做的
You were right to leave. You did what you wanted to do.
我给你打电话时 总有不同的女人回答
When I call you, a different woman always answers.
但是我从没有在她们的声音里听出来...
But I never heard in any of their voices...
她们真的爱你 我也不知道
that they really loved you. I would've known.
有时我真想看到你稳定下来...
All the same, I'd have liked to see you settled...
爱一个人
loving someone.
但你生活在罗马 这里太阴沉了
But your life is there. Here there are only ghosts.
忘了她吧 多多
Let go, Toto.
这是我的广场 它是我的
It's my square. It's mine.
检查好了就放
Check the leader. Roll when you're ready.
我喜欢你的电影 非常喜欢
Right. And I liked your film. Terrific.
谢谢
Thanks.